בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is צדי ט, Tzadi Tes,
99, and we pick up on צדי ח עמוד ב.
Tzadi Ches Amud Beis. So we literally one line from the bottom,
we had spent yesterday discussing a little bit about how when they
carried the beams, it did not make for a covered רשות הרבים.
Reshus Harabbim. And then for debates about exactly whether the tops of
the beams were angled or not, which led to how far down
the curtains draped. Now we get to have a few more discussions
about the beams before we get back to discussing carrying. So let's
take a look, last line of צדי ח עמוד ב. Tzadi Ches
Amud Beis. תנו רבנן חרוצים היו קרשים Tanu Rabbanan charutzim hayu kerashim
the beams were carved, not carved, although like cut
into וחלולים היו אדנים vachallulim hayu adanim and the sockets were hollow.
So basically all that means is, I mean like if you look
here, there's a picture in the רש"י, Rashi, basically means that at
the bottom
of the post, anyway, you had right the whole thing was a
rectangular solid. But it has to end with two little pegs at
the bottom, two feet that are going to go into the hollow
of two sockets. So the sockets were sort of squares with a
hollow in it. And in order to make the bottom אמה amah
into two feet, you had to cut in, right? You had to
go in and you know what was it that Michelangelo said? Somebody
said how do you make the David? He says you start with
a block of marble and you cut away everything that isn't the
David. Right? So here, you have this, and you have to turn
this into two little pegs that are going to go into the
what do you call it, into the socket, so you cut away
everything that isn't the peg. Right? So you cut like this, and
you cut like this, and whatever, and you cut like this, and
then you have your two feet. But yes, so that's what it
means חרוצים. charutzim. They were carved into. And then you made sockets
that were
hollow so they could then, you know, that they could then go
into like the sockets, right?
So that's all it means. You carved into the feet so that
you made the bottom of the post so you made it into
little pegs, and you had hollow sockets, and that's how it fit
together.
Okay, now top of צדי ט עמוד א. Tzadi Tes Amud Alef.
ונראים קרסים בלולאות ככוכבים ברקיע. Venirim krasim belula'ot kekochavim barakia.
Totally different point, not about the beams but about the curtains above
or, you know, the roof above made out of curtains. Now, if
the תורה Torah says that what you did is you had five
curtains sewn together and five curtains sewn together, and then you had
like rings at the edge of the curtain and like hooks that
would link the two sets of curtains together. So those קרסים, krasim,
those hooks, would be would if you looked up, right, so they
were so you had this whole roof of curtains and then right
in the middle, you had all these like, you know, gold-colored copper
I mean I said gold-colored copper, you know, rings and hooks or
whatever. So that would appear like stars in the sky. Of course,
you don't really know how you would see them, that might depend
on the lighting or whatever, but okay that's the point.
Was that the intention to recreate the sense of sky?
It's an interesting question. I mean, it's not like that the curtains
were all made out of blue, you know, so but
it's like a poetic
I know, it's a nice very imagery. Right. It's very sort of
concrete discussion. I know, I was thinking about that too that maybe
it's hinting that somehow that was the imagery that was trying to
be created. But but it's not like the curtains were all blue
or anything like that. All right. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now, יריעות
תחתונות של תכלת. yeri'ot tachtonos shel techeiles. Now the גמרא Gemara even
tells you what they were made out of. תכלת וארגמן ותולעת שני.
Techeiles ve'argaman vesola'as shani. Right? So they were blue and they were
crimson and they were ארגמן, argaman, they were like royal purple. Scarlet
well, תולעת שני tola'as shani is the scarlet. ארגמן argaman is like
a royal purple. So anyway there was this mix of blue and
purple and red. ושש Veshesh and of linen. עליונות, Elyonos, the top
ones, which were you know so those were the very colorful bottom
ones. ושל עליונות, Veshel elyonos, the top ones which were linen, as
we said yesterday, those were מעשה
עזים, ma'aseh izim, those were just made out of straight goat hair.
So it sounds like the top ones which were there to protect
the bottom ones were much easier. But it goes on to say:
וגדולה חכמה שנאמרה בעליונות יותר ממה שנאמרה בתחתונות. Ugdolah chochmah shene'emrah be'elyonos
yoser mimas shene'emrah betachtonos.
But the skill that it took to weave the top curtains was
greater than that of the bottom ones, which is interesting, I mean
it's all just one material, why does it take more skill? דאילו
בתחתונות כתיב, De'ilu betachtonos kesiv, by the bottom curtains it says: וכל
אשה חכמת לב בידיה טוו. Vechol ishah chachamas lev beyadeha tavu.
Every every woman of a wise heart of, you know, of skill,
would weave with her hands or would spin with her hands. ואילו
בעליונות כתיב, Ve'ilu be'elyonos כתיב, and regarding making the top curtains it
said: וכל הנשים אשר נשא לבן אותן בחכמה. Vechol hanashim asher nasa
liban osan bechochmah. All women whose hearts lifted them up with wisdom.
טוו את העזים Tavu es ha'izim and they spun
the goat. spun the goats, the goat hair. So now we're going
to explain why it took greater skill, דתניא משמיה דרבי נחמיה Detanya
mishmeih deRabbi Nechemiah we taught in the name of Rabbi Nechemiah something
we taught about a month ago, שטוף בעיזים וטווי מן העיזים. Shatuf
ba'izim vetavui min ha'izim.
The wisdom was that they had the goats go into the river
and that's the way they cleaned the wool, the hair, even on
the goats themselves, and then they spun it straight off of the
backs of the goats. So therefore the ability to spin the thread
straight off of the backs of the goats, that required a special
skill. Why exactly they did that other than to prove how skillful
they were, maybe it was more efficient, I don't know, but that's
a דרשה drashah from טוו את העיזים, tavu et ha'izim, they spun
the goats itself, they spun directly from the goat.
Okay, questions like a couple דפים dapim before whether
that was as if you did it it was מלאכה. melachah. Yeah,
the גמרא Gemara quoted this פסוק pasuk and said well maybe they
had חכמה יתירה, chochmah yetirah, therefore a normal person would not be
חייב chayav because it would be a שינוי shinuy for a normal
person to do it. This is where it was quoted earlier. Okay,
so that's the end of the discussion of the beams. Now back
to still in the context of הלוויים haLevi'im but back to the
מלאכה melachah of carrying. It says if you have right two balconies
on the same side of רשות הרבים Reshut haRabbim and you pass
from one to the other you're חייב chayav because that's what the
לוויים Levi'im did in the משכן, Mishkan, they passed from one wagon
to the next along the length of רשות הרבים Reshut haRabbim and
the רשות הרבים Reshut haRabbim ran underneath them. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב שתי גזוזטראות, Amar Rav shtei gezustra'ot, that's
about the two balconies.
אמר רב משמיה
דרבי חייא Amar Rav mishmeih deRabbi Chiya עגלות תחתיהן וביניהן וצידיהן רשות
הרבים. Agalot tachteihen beneihen vetzideihen Reshut haRabbim. So we said this yesterday,
underneath them, between the wagons, and their sides were all רשות הרבים.
Reshut haRabbim. Okay, now, so again we said that yesterday, we spoke
about didn't the beams cover it, was it רשות הרבים Reshut haRabbim
covered? Now let's see where the גמרא Gemara focuses.
אמר אביי Amar Abaye בין עגלה לעגלה bein agalah le'agalah between one
wagon and the next כמלא אורך עגלה kemlo orech agalah was the
length of one wagon.
וכמה אורך עגלה vechamah orech agalah and what was the length of
a wagon? חמש אמות. chamesh amot. It was five אמות. amot. So
what does this mean? So רש"י Rashi says five אמות, chamesh amot,
excuse me, five אמות. chamesh amot. So what does this mean? So
רש"י Rashi says this is what I told you yesterday, I'm first
going to explain it like רש"י Rashi and then I'll tell you
תוספות's Tosafot's explanation. So רש"י Rashi says you have one wagon, right?
It's sort of five אמות amot long. Okay, and you've got another
wagon five אמות amot long. They could be separated from one another
five אמות. amot. But you also have two wagons side by side,
okay? And it's also five אמות amot wide. שתי אמות ומחצה Shtei
amot u'mechtza two and a half אמות amot on the base, and
then an אמה amah and a quarter on each side for the
wheels, the width of the wheels and so on. So the entire
width of a wagon is five אמות. amot.
Could the wheels be that wide?
Yeah, אמה ומחצה, amah u'mechtza, what is that, two feet? Okay, it's
a big thick big wagon wheel. Anyway, and then another one also
from the edge of one to the other was five אמות, amot,
and there were five אמות amot between them. Okay, so let's see
anyway what the גמרא Gemara says. Yes.
No, you told me about the width that's why they're not back
to back.
They were both. There were two by two front and back. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says, but first we're going to talk
not about the width of covering the street, we're going to talk
about the length of the wagon was five אמות. amot. Now you
remember the גמרא Gemara yesterday spoke about the fact that you had
the beams an אמה ומחצה amah u'mechtza right going down like this
and like this and like this. So if it's five אמות amot
it's three columns of beams. Then the גמרא Gemara switched to say
that the beams were actually at their edge and they were even
they were one אמה. amah. And so then you had four columns
of one אמה amah each and a little space. Right, that's what
the גמרא Gemara said. So now the גמרא Gemara says, so we're
talking about its length being five אמות. amot. It says, למה לי
בארבע ופלגא סגי? Lama li be'arba u'palga sagi?
Why do you need why do you need it to be five
אמות amot long? Four and a half is enough if you do
one and a half width right alongside each other, three columns, that's
four and a half. Or even if you understood that they put
it at the narrow end and it's one, who needs a gap
of a full אמה, amah, a gap of a half of an
אמה amah should be enough. גמרא Gemara says: No, כי היכי דלא
ליצדו קרשים. Ki heichi dela litzdu kerushim. No, you still wanted to
give them a little bit more space so they shouldn't rub up
against one another and that would wear away at them. So again,
it's not exactly clear right how do you keep these tall columns
without it all collapsing inside anyway, which is why the תוספות Tosafot
basically says that they alternated, it was sort of like laying bricks,
you sort of staggered it one column to the next. But anyway,
so however the גמרא's Gemara understanding why you need a little air
space, it says if you would compress it too much it would
all rub up against one another and it would not be good.
So you needed a little extra air space. And therefore you were
able to have either three columns or four columns. Okay, אמר רבא
Amar Rava צידי עגלה. tzidei agalah. Now we're getting to what I
mentioned to you before which is going to be a little more
interesting which is the width across the street.
צידי עגלה כמלא רוחב עגלה. Tzidei agalah kemlo rochav agalah. The sides
were like the width of the עגלה. agalah. וכמה רוחב עגלה? Vechamah
rochav agalah? שתי אמות ומחצה. Shtei amot u'mechtza. So that's what I
told you before, the entire base here of your wagon was two
and a half אמות. amot. The additional sides taken up by the
wagon wheels on each side... is another two and a half אמות.
amot. An אמה amah and a quarter for each wagon wheel. So
from the outer edge of one wagon wheel to the outer edge
of the other is a full five אמות. amot. Okay. So now
and then you would have two side by side. This is according
to רש''י. Rashi. One minute. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
וכמה
רוחב עגלה שתי אמות וחציה. Ve'kama rochav agala shtei amot ve'chetzya. למה
לי באמתא ופלגא סגי? Lama li be'amta upalga sagi? So the גמרא
Gemara says why did the base, forget the wagon wheels, have to
be two and a half אמות? amot? Shouldn't it be enough to
be an אמה amah and a half? Now what does this mean?
The way it would operate is, let me
show you what I showed you yesterday.
You have your wagon, you have your big thick wheels, let's say
this is two and a half, like one and a quarter on
each side, these are the wheels, right?
This is one and a quarter, why did I draw a half?
I'm sorry, I'm thinking. Okay, that's fine. Anyway, here is your wagon,
right, and it's sort of going this way. According to רש''י Rashi
what you would do is you'd have these two wagons side by
side, and you'd lay the beams, right, if you remember רש''י Rashi
says, so this is, you'd lay one beam like this, and then
this one would have one beam like this. Okay, so this would
have, and this would be supported, it would be, there would be
an overhang, right? So if this whole thing is five from the
outer edge, so there's also an overhang here of two and a
half, right, per side, right? Yeah, so that's basically how רש''י, Rashi,
right, how רש''י Rashi imagines it. So by the way, and this
would be important, from this edge to this edge, if each one
is an overhang of two and a half and each one of
these is five, it's going to be fifteen from the edges of
the outer wheel of there to the other outer wheel.
And you've got it like right smacking up against each other.
We'll talk about that in a minute. So what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is, why do you need a full two and a
half אמה amah base here to support the beams? What if, why
couldn't the base be a little bit more narrow? Why couldn't the
wagon be narrower? Now the answer's obvious, I mean, you know, that's
not very stable. I mean even this way, I mean you only
have a two and a half thing. The real overhang by the
way is not two and a half, if you include the overhang
that's overhanging the wheel, it's really like five אמות amot from the
edge, you know, that's overhanging the wheel. So you have a two
and a half אמה amah base underneath supporting a beam which is,
did I do that right? I think I did. One, no, I'm
sorry, it's one and a quarter, what is it, three and three
quarters? Something like that. Six, seven and a half, yeah, three and
three quarters. Okay, so you have a lot of, you have three
and three quarters on each side being supported by a two and
a half, you know, sort of wagon in the middle, it's not
super stable. But we'll get to both all these problems in a
minute, but the גמרא Gemara is asking an even more radical question,
let the actual wagon in the middle be even more narrow. So
the גמרא Gemara says,
so it says למה לי באמתא ופלגא סגי? Lama li be'amta upalga
sagi? Why do you need a full two and a half אמה
amah base here to support this beam of each wagon going across
lengthwise? Why isn't
an אמה amah and a half enough?
So כי היכי דלא לידודי קרשים, ki heichi d'lo lidudi krashim, in
order so the beams should not, you know, should not, should not
move, should not, you know, should not sway, in order to give
more stability to the beams. So now the גמרא Gemara says אלא
דקיימא לן דרך רשות הרבים שש עשרה אמה, Ela d'kaima lan derech
reshut harabim shesh esrei amah, but we say that a רשות הרבים
reshut harabim the minimum width of a רשות הרבים reshut harabim is
sixteen אמה. amah. And presumably we learned this from what they did
in the מדבר. midbar. So the גמרא Gemara says אנן דגמרינן לה
ממשכן, Anan d'gamrinan lah mi'mishkan, we would learn it out from the
משכן. Mishkan. משכן חמיסר הוה, Mishkan chamisar hava, the משכן Mishkan it's
fifteen.
So from the outer edge of one wheel to the next is
five and five and apparently they're right up against one another, oh
actually they're not, the beams are overhanging, right, because there's five in
between as well, so the beams are overhanging, so from here to
here is
fifteen, five, five, and five in the middle is fifteen.
So the גמרא Gemara says how do you get sixteen?
אמתא יתירתא הואי, Amta yetirta havai, no there was an extra אמה
amah דהוה קאי בין לוי, d'hava kai bein Levi, that that's where
the לוי Levi would be walking alongside the wagon. דכי משתלפי קרשים
הוה נקיט להו, d'ki mishtalfi krashim hava nakit lehu, if the beams
would start to
slip, right, you have a לוי Levi walking right alongside here, so
if these beams would start to slip he'd be
able to, you know, he'd be able to adjust them. Maybe you'd
have another לוי Levi walk right alongside here so he could adjust,
walk alongside the wagon if they began to. So from this wheel
to this wheel is fifteen, then you have a half an אמה
amah on each side, maybe the לוי Levi had a whole אמה,
amah, the לוי Levi would move from one side to the next,
but anyway that's how you get sixteen אמות. amot. This is the
way רש''י Rashi explains it. And תוספות Tosafot points out, yeah, okay,
but the middle part is very tight, the beams don't, תוספות Tosafot
points out there are a lot of problems with this explanation. Number
one, as Michael says, if you have these overhangs, the beams are
like banging against each other side by side, it's going to rub
away the beams and then anyway it's going to cause them to
fall and it's not going to be very stable. Number two, תוספות
Tosafot says, even with two and a half, says what is it
if you have a two and a half base to support an
overhang of three and three quarters on each side? It's extremely unstable.
What the heck is going on here?
Actually, says תוספות, Tosafot, what you actually had was is that one
wagon here, okay, and that this one wagon...
so you have one wagon that's going like
this, okay.
Just want to double check one point about the תוספות. Tosafot.
Right,
right, right.
So תוספות Tosafot says, yeah, that's it. So this wagon is ten
אמות amot long. Remember the גמרא Gemara said that the wheels, the
thickness of the wheels was two and a half אמות? amot? רש״י
Rashi divided it. He made each wheel one and a quarter אמות.
amot. תוספות Tosafot says no, the wheel, each wheel individually was a
thickness, a very thick wheel of two and a half אמות. amot.
So you have two and a half here, you have two and
a half here, so the entire one single wagon is fifteen. And
the space on the inside is ten. Now the space on the
inside being ten works out very nicely because what else was ten?
The קרשים, krashim, the length of the קרשים. krashim. So actually it
was very easy. We did not have overhang, right? You had the
one thing, the whole thing going the length of the wagon, the
whole thing was fifteen. Right, and that's sort of what's, and that's
what's going on here, and that's the two and a half and
then the לוי Levi was over here, anyway that's how תוספות Tosafot
explained it. Now if you remember yesterday, he said five
אמות amot wide, but didn't we say this five we just had
over...?
No, two and a half of each wheel at the edge. סתם
אורחא דמילתא stam orcha demilta five אמות?
amot? חמישה? chamisha?
Ah,
thank you. So what about the fact that the גמרא Gemara said
five and not ten? Right, so what תוספות Tosafot actually said was,
it's describing here is not that there was somehow... or actually you
know what I oversimplified it, I'm sorry, I apologize. Because תוספות Tosafot
actually says what it would look like is that you actually would
have this, it would still be one structure, okay, you would have
it look like this, as if it were two wagons combined, you
would have four wheels going underneath the base, okay, two on the
outside and two underneath the base, four wheels going under, and this
would be, it wouldn't be two wagons, but this would just be
like, you know, it would be there would be like a wall
going up here so the beam would lay across like that, okay,
but this would all be, you know, essentially it'd be one floor.
You'd have one floor, I don't know if I'm drawing it well,
but one floor, you have walls going up in the middle to
support so it wouldn't actually lay on the inside, it would still
sort of be on top, okay, but the wheels down here would
be would be would be all part of one structure. What was
the five?
What did the גמרא Gemara say five? What did they do that
for?
Each half was five.
You mean each half was five?
Let me
double-check again.
They across? No, like they were.
Yeah,
תוספות Tosafot says that this was five אמות, amot, but then it
says between one עגלה agala and the other was the width of
the עגלה. agala. This is five אמות, amot, this is I guess
right, two and a half, right, so I did not draw this
just right. So תוספות Tosafot anyway says this is two and a
half, this is five, this is two and a half, okay. So
it says that you have two and a half plus the width
of the wheel is five, two and a half plus the width
of the wheel is five, the space between is five, but this
is all really one structure. And that's why the גמרא Gemara was
able to ask why did it why couldn't you do it even
a little bit different? Why couldn't you make these walls a little
bit even narrower, even one and a quarter, and then that would
be too unstable? Okay, so anyway תוספות Tosafot basically explains it similar
to רש״י, Rashi, except what רש״י Rashi had is two structures, תוספות
Tosafot makes one structure, and whereas רש״י Rashi had beams coming out
from the two different structures banging up against one another and you
had to coordinate two different things, תוספות Tosafot just says they're long
enough for one ten אמה amah beam all the way across. What?
To make it flexible to go around corners?
Oh, I don't know, that
much I can't answer.
You have a roadbed but you have four wheels?
Yeah, that could be. Okay. I hear the point. I don't know.
Alright, go ahead.
The idea that it's if it's like a street is nowadays sixteen
אמות amot therefore it's automatically רשות הרבים reshut harabbim and then we
can't have...?
No, if it's sixteen אמות amot it's automatically רשות הרבים, reshut harabbim,
if it's less than sixteen אמות amot it can't be a רשות
הרבים. reshut harabbim. One of the criteria, it's necessary but not sufficient.
One of the criteria is רשות הרבים reshut harabbim sixteen אמות. amot.
But anyway, but the basic point according to תוספות Tosafot I hope
you see is that It allows for greater stability because you're not
trying to get two beams along that length, you're only trying to
get one beam, and that it doesn't require that the wagon somehow
be perfectly aligned, you know, and that the beams don't rub up
against another, basically combines it all into one wagon with compartments as
opposed to two separate structures. Yes.
This has the אורחא דצופייא orcha d'tzufaya like, you know, the other
one according to תוספות, Tosafos, right?
The five gap is between the front and the back.
Yeah. And then when he says עגלה שתים ומחצה, agala shtayim u'mechetza,
that's just from, like, yeah, it doesn't mean עגלה.
agala. What תוספות Tosafos says is what we're calling an עגלה agala
is from the outer wall to the first inner wall and from
this outer wall to the first inner wall because underneath the first
inner wall was where an extra wheel was located. But really, it's
all one structure and the beam is being laid across. All right.
Let's take a look now as we move on to the next
משנה. Mishnah. Enough with the לויים Levi'im and the משכן, Mishkan, back
to carry. חוליית הבור והסלע. Chulyat habor vehasela. So a חולייה chulya
of a בור bor is the dirt dug out of a well
to make a well, but they would create as a mound around
the opening of the well. So presumably, like, you know, just as
a safety thing, somebody wouldn't walk right into the well. So you
have a well dug into the ground and you have a mound
of dirt around it protecting it. That mound of dirt might be
itself a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Why? If it's ten טפחים tefachim
high, right, and four טפחים tefachim by four טפחים tefachim in its
area, okay, you know, its sort of space, so that's a רשות
היחיד. reshus hayachid. The same way if you have a rock. It
doesn't, a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid is not only a standard scenario
where you have the floor and then walls and you have a,
like, hollow on the inside, a cavity on the inside. Even if
you have a mound that's ten
טפחים tefachim high with four טפחים tefachim as a base, four by
four, so that's also a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Why? Because we
assume like if you've got—and I'm showing a, I'm going to spill
this coffee, but if this is your mound, this cup of coffee,
right, these ten טפחים tefachim walls and you've got the base up
here, these walls extend upwards and therefore the roof, the top here
is a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. The same way like a roof
of a building is a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, but even if
the entire building was filled with dirt, it's not just because those
walls work for the inside. Even if the entire building was filled
with dirt, the roof would be a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid because
the edges are seen as continuing up. So that's what this משנה
Mishnah says. חוליית הבור, Chulyat habor, that mound of earth around the
well, והסלע, vehasela, or just a rock, שאין גבוהין עשרה, she'ein gevohin
asara, that they are ten טפחים tefachim high, ורחבים ארבעה, urerchavim arba'a,
and are four טפחים tefachim by four טפחים tefachim wide.
We're
not talking about the cavity yet. The גמרא Gemara will talk about
it. We are not talking about the cavity. הנוטל מהן והנותן על
גבן, Hanotel mehen vehanoten al gaban, if you take something off of
the top of the rock or off of the top of that
mound or you put something on it and presumably you're standing in
the street, in the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, then חייב, chayav, you're
חייב. chayav. פחות מכן, Pachot miken, if they do not have, if
they have less than those dimensions, less than ten טפחים tefachim high
or less than four by four wide—and I should say four by
four is not just the area, it doesn't matter if you have
sixteen square טפחים, tefachim, it has to be four in each direction—if
you have anything less than those, than those dimensions, פטור, patur, you
are exempt. It is not a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. It would
be depending, it would even be like a part of רשות הרבים
reshus harabbim or it would be a מקום פטור makom patur depending
on exactly which ways the dimensions were, were off. Yes.
I seem to remember he said before that even, when they had
these wells in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim for שבת Shabbos issues, they'd
make like these, he'd make like these things
around them, right?
Are we going to get to that? I'm trying to understand why
that was necessary. If we're saying it's a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
making something around it would make it even worse. We're already saying
it's a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, so what are those...
Well, let's take a minute because we're going to look at the
גמרא Gemara and discuss the well itself. Right now we're just discussing
the mounds by the well. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
למה לי למתני חוליית הבור והסלע? Lama li lemasni chulyat habor vehasela?
Why do you have to say the mound by the well or
a rock? ליתני הבור והסלע. Lisni habor vehasela.
Just say the well and the rock. Meaning the mound is the
same הלכה halacha as the rock. It's basically telling me you've got
a big solid that's, you know, and therefore the space on top
is a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. The well tells me a different
idea. The well tells me a more classic רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
It tells me a space where you've got a cavity that has
ten טפחים tefachim walls going alongside it. And by the way, even
that's a חידוש. chiddush. Why is the well a חידוש? chiddush? Why
isn't that just a really standard רשות היחיד? reshus hayachid? You have
a cavity surrounded by four walls. Because although it's surrounded by things
ten טפחים tefachim on all sides, I mean, would you necessarily call
that a wall? It's like it's not like it's a separate entity,
right? It's not like where does the wall start and end? It's
not like it's got a thickness. It's like the entire earth, Planet
Earth, is the wall. So anyway, what?
That's a hole.
Yes, we're talking about a hole.
Right, so that's what I'm saying, like a regular...
I know, I'm just saying there's an element of a חידוש chiddush
as well. Just saying that this, like a hole in the ground,
is a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Yes, it is normal in the
way that it's four here and ten on each side and it's
got a cavity, but it's not totally normal. It's not like you
actually have an independent thing called a wall. You have the entire
earth, which is your wall.
Were they lined with stones or...
Maybe, but even without that. I mean, so the point is both
of those are רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. A rock is a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid even though it doesn't have a cavity. A hole
is a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid although it has a cavity, it
doesn't have the sort of normal types of walls. It has one...
But again, they're not like they don't have endpoints. Okay, so those
are two חידושים. Chiddushim. So just tell me that. Tell me הבור
והסלע, Habor Vehasela, the well and a rock. חוליית הבור והסלע. Chulias
habor vehasela. So why did it have to say חוליית הבור, Chulias
habor, the mound near the well? The mound near the well is
just like a rock, it's not an interesting case. So מסייע ליה
לרבי יוחנן, Mesaya lei le-Rabbi Yochanan, this supports רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
דאמר רבי יוחנן, De'amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, בור
וחולייתה מצטרפין לעשרה, Bor vechuliyasa mitztarfin l'asara,
that this is what Michael is saying, not just the mound by
the well. The mound plus the actual hollow itself combines to ten.
Now, what way does it combine to ten? In two possible ways.
רש״י Rashi says the גמרא Gemara is talking about one of them.
תוספות Tosafos says the גמרא Gemara is talking about the other. Okay,
one way it combines to ten is
here is your ground, come along, you've dug a well, then you
put some dirt around it, right? Whatever, this is a two-dimensional cut.
So רש״י Rashi says that the combining for ten is, if your
well is only five טפחים, Tefachim, whatever, doesn't matter, it could be
six, and this is five טפחים. Tefachim. So therefore, in this case,
if you're standing at the bottom of the well, right, you have
ten טפחים Tefachim wall, five made by the sides of the well,
five made by the mound alongside. So for somebody down here, you're
in a רשות היחיד. Reshus hayachid. Okay, is that clear? Yes? If
you're standing over here, right, so if you threw something down, obviously,
you know, it would be a... you'd be putting it into a
רשות היחיד. Reshus hayachid. But if you put something on this mound,
you're not putting it in a רשות היחיד Reshus hayachid because that
mound is only five טפחים Tefachim high. The top of the mound
isn't רשות היחיד, Reshus hayachid, but the well is. The well is
combined with both the walls underneath and the mounds that you've put.
So the mound is מקום פטור? Makom p'tur? What? Is the mound
מקום פטור? Makom p'tur?
The top of the mound? Yeah, or whatever, depends how it's used,
צידי רשות הרבים, Tzidei reshus harabbim, whatever, yes. But that's how רש״י
Rashi explains it. Now, the problem with that explanation is that the
משנה Mishna says הנוטל מהן והנותן על גבן, Hanotel mehen vehanosen al
gaban,
if you put on them or take from or put on top
of them. What on top of is this scenario talking about according
to רש״י? Rashi? The only thing that would be חייב Chayav is
if you put in the well, but not if you put on
the top of the mound, which is what the משנה Mishna says.
Oh,
so what תוספות Tosafos says is, we're not talking about combining to
get your ten, there's another dimension we care about, which is the
four. So what תוספות Tosafos is saying is, your mounds are actually
ten טפחים Tefachim high. We don't care, okay, we don't actually care
about this, that's not important. Your mound is ten טפחים Tefachim high.
But the problem is is that this is a טפח Tefach and
this is a טפח Tefach and the space between them is two
טפחים. Tefachim. So when it says the mound and the well combined,
they don't combine for the height. You don't need height. They combine,
which means the gap here allows you to consider this whole thing
a four טפח Tefach space. Now, why does it consider four... you
can't use the whole four טפחים. Tefachim. So come אביי Abaye and
he says, well, yeah, you could put a... you could put a
plank there. So since you could put a plank there, right, that
makes this all considered to be one unit. Even if you don't
put the plank. Even if you don't put the plank, okay, because
in theory you could... now, that doesn't mean that if you didn't
have the well context, you just had like a little post here
and you just had a little post here, and I put something
on top of one of these things, I'd say, oh, that's a
רשות היחיד Reshus hayachid because in theory I could make a plank
to the next thing. Presumably, this is because it is seen of
as part of the whole... of the whole apparatus of the well.
So because it's seen of as some unit and in theory you
could put a plank between them, that makes it considered like you
have the four טפחים Tefachim across. So תוספות Tosafos has the combination
being in the width, not in the height.
But it's the same thing about רש״י? Rashi?
Yes, if you put something on the top... הנותן והנוטל Hanosen vehanotel
could be if you... if it's covered and you put something on
the top.
Yeah, I mean, turn רש״י Rashi
into a
תוספות, Tosafos, but...
No, but that wouldn't be true.
If it was only five טפחים, Tefachim, the גמרא Gemara is clear
about this in another case. If there's only five טפחים Tefachim here
and the rest... if this is five and the rest of the
five is underground, it is only a רשות היחיד Reshus hayachid for
the guy standing on the bottom. If you're using it from out
here and using the mound, you know, it's not a רשות היחיד.
Reshus hayachid.
But what if you have it if it's covered and you place
something on top of it, so the guy outside is not...
but then still from his perspective, it's a... it's a five טפח
Tefach thing, it's not a ten טפח Tefach thing. Okay, yes.
But what does רש״י Rashi say about the excess
dirt, the...? What? Less than טפח Tefach then? Like the mound itself?
Can it be even a טפח? Tefach?
No.
What do you mean?
For רש״י, Rashi, for רש״י Rashi the well itself is four טפחים.
Tefachim. Yeah. It doesn't matter what the length, the width of the
mound.
Right, because for רש״י Rashi the only... correct, the only thing that's
considered רשות היחיד Reshus hayachid is at the bottom.
Inside the well.
Inside the well. Right. Okay.
All right.
So now... so anyway, so again, it's really based on different גמרות,
Gemaros, they don't disagree that either of those scenarios work. The question
is just which one to say the גמרא Gemara is talking about.
about. Let's say you take it from the
outside and put it inside the well, and you're חייב. chayav.
Then you're חייב. chayav.
Yes. Sure.
It goes inside.
What do you mean it goes inside the well? I know, let's
say you threw an object inside a well. Let's say you lowered
your bucket in, so you put your bucket into the well in
order to draw water out. You're on top. Yes.
So that's a problem.
Yes, it is a problem. רש״י Rashi it is...
it's only for you you're inside the well.
No, no. The inside is defined as...
okay I see. The inside is defined as רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
So if you're on the outside, if you put it down into
the well, you're putting it into a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, okay?
But if you're using just the mound, right, I don't mean you
have to be standing in the well, okay?
But according to רש״י, Rashi, if you let's say draw your water
out of the well or whatever, you're taking it out of a
רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, okay?
That's the point. All right, so let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly,
בור ברשות הרבים, bor bi-reshus ha-rabim, עמוק עשרה ורחב ארבעה. amok asara
ve-rachav arba'ah. So it's ten deep and it's four wide. It's a
pit. Right, the pit. אין ממלאין הימנו בשבת. Ein memalin himenu b'Shabbos.
You cannot draw water because then you're taking... the outside is either
a כרמלית karmelis or רשות הרבים, reshus ha-rabim, so you're drawing water
from a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid into a רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim
or at least into a כרמלית. karmelis. This is what... right. And
this is what Michael was talking about before, which is that in
some circumstances they allowed you to make a... now certainly if you
make a real wall around the area, but they even allowed you
to make like just the corners in some circumstances if it's a
public well or whatever to allow people to come in and to
draw water and to define the space right in the vicinity as
רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. But if you haven't done some type of
a wall, then you're taking from רשות היחיד reshus hayachid into whatever
the space around outside is, either a כרמלית karmelis or רשות הרבים.
reshus ha-rabim. אלא אם כן עשו לו מחיצה גבוהה עשרה טפחים. Ela
im kein asu lo mechitzah gevohah asara tefachim. So if you want
to fix it and you want to draw water you have to
make a ten טפחים tefachim wall around that well. ואין שותים מהם
בשבת, ve-ein shotim me-hem b'Shabbos, and if you want to drink from
it, what are you going to do? We just said you can't
draw water, what are you going to do? אלא אם כן הכניס
לתוכו ראשו ורובו. Ela im kein hichnis l'tocho rosho ve-rubo. You would
have to actually get your whole body or the majority of your
body into the well and, right, pretty dangerous depending on how deep
the well is and to drink. Because even if you just were
to say,
no, no, no, not a problem, I'll just like lean over and
draw water and drink and I won't take it away. But no,
if you're not the majority of your body, we're afraid you'll like
stand up and then bring it out of the רשות היחיד reshus
hayachid vicinity into wherever you're standing. So it has to be seriously
leaning into the well, the majority of your body, which you got
to figure... it does not sound like a good idea. Exactly.
Or the bucket? What? Is the bucket enough to put it in?
Is the bucket enough? What do you mean? You draw the bucket
up, but if you took the bucket out of the sort of
air space of the well, you'd be taking it from רשות היחיד
reshus hayachid into a כרמלית. karmelis.
You mean he's saying you just keep your... you're leaning in with
the bucket in your hand, you haven't...
no, but it's not enough. Even if the bucket is fully in
and you're leaning over, this ברייתא braisa is
saying it's not enough because we're afraid you'll... you'll stand up and
you'll take the bucket with you. So you have to actually have
the majority of your body into the well, which is pretty dangerous.
Okay. Now and the end, which is the point we were making,
ובור וחוליתה מצטרפין לעשרה. ve-bor ve-chuliyasa mitztarfin l'asara.
And the בור bor and the mound around it combined to ten.
Okay, now this by the way, the מצטרפין לעשרה, mitztarfin l'asara, this
is explicitly, right, like... like רש״י, Rashi, because here... actually, no, ר׳
יוחנן׳ס Rebbi Yochanan's statement as well, מצטרפין לעשרה, mitztarfin l'asara, is exactly
like רש״י, Rashi, which is the case of ten. תוספות Tosafos just
says, right, so תוספות Tosafos agrees, תוספות Tosafos agrees that ר׳ יוחנן׳ס
Rebbi Yochanan's statement and this
ברייתא braisa is the רש״י Rashi scenario, is the מצטרפין לעשרה. mitztarfin
l'asara. But what תוספות Tosafos says is when we apply what ר׳
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan said to our משנה, mishna, we were saying this
case. The same way ר׳ יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan said the five and
the five get ten, it would also be true if it's the
combined for the width. The reason תוספות Tosafos is saying that is
again because the משנה mishna talks about putting on top of the
mound. It doesn't talk about putting in the well. Okay, so רש״י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafos don't disagree with either ways of combining. The
only question is, ר׳ יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says combining for ten, are
we saying the משנה׳ס mishna's talking about the same, which is what
רש״י Rashi said, or according to תוספות Tosafos we're saying the same
way ר׳ יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan said they combine for ten, they would
also combine width-wise along the hollow of the... of the well. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara continues. בעי מיניה רב מרדכי מרבה. Ba'ei minei
Rav Mordechai mei-Rabbah. רב מרדכי Rav Mordechai asked from רבה. Rabbah. עמוד
ברשות הרבים גבוה עשרה ורחב ארבעה. Amud bi-reshus ha-rabim gavo'ah asara ve-rachav
arba'ah. You have a... a beam in רשות הרבים, reshus ha-rabim, a
stand, that is... that is ten high and four wide, okay? Sounds
just like the rock of our משנה. mishna. וזרק ונח על גביו,
Ve-zarak ve-nach al gabav, and you threw something and it landed on
the... on the top of it. Okay, that's a common scenario. You
threw from רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim and it landed on a רשות
היחיד. reshus hayachid. Should be very straightforward. מהו, Mahu, what do we
say? מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan, do we say הרי עקירה באיסור הרי
הנחה באיסור? harei akirah b'issur harei hanachah b'issur? You picked it up
באיסור b'issur from רשות הרבים, reshus ha-rabim, you put it down באיסור
b'issur in רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, right? So therefore you're חייב. chayav.
או דלמא, O dilma, or do we say, כיון דממקום פטור קאתיא,
keivan d'mimakom patur ka-asya, but wait, here you are in רשות הרבים...
reshus ha-rabim... has an airspace of ten. You threw something from the
רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabim, it went higher than ten, so that it
could then fall, right, on the top of this beam. So obviously
somewhere in the trajectory it was higher than ten. So it went
from the רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim to a מקום פטור makom patur
and then to רשות היחיד. Reshus HaYachid. Maybe you should be exempt.
Okay. Do we say כיון דמקום פטור קאתיא, Kivan de-makom patur ka-asya,
no, you would not be חייב. chayav. אמר ליה, Amar lei, he
said to him, מתניתין היא. Matnisin hi. What do you mean? It's
a משנה. Mishna. A משנה Mishna talks about a rock עשרה טפחים
asara tefachim high in רשות הרבים. Reshus HaRabim. It's obviously you're חייב.
chayav. אתא שייליה לרב יוסף. Asa sheilei le-Rav Yosef. He went and
asked Rav Yosef. He didn't like that answer. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
Rav Yosef said to him, מתניתין היא, Matnisin hi, it's a משנה.
Mishna. He didn't like that. אתא שייליה לאביי. Asa sheilei le-Abaye. Went
and asked Abaye. אמר ליה, Amar lei, Abaye said, מתניתין היא, Matnisin
hi, it's a משנה. Mishna. אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said to
them, כולהו ברוקא דהדדי תפיתו. Kulhu be-ruka de-hadadi tapisu. You're all spitting
each other's spit. Okay. You're sharing each other's spit. Okay. Which is,
you're all saying the same thing and I don't find it interesting.
So אמר ליה, Amar lei, so they said to him, what do
you mean?
הא לא תסברה? Ha lo tisbera? You don't agree with this?
והתנן, Ve-hatnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishna, הנוטל מהן והנותן על
גבן ha-notel me-hen ve-ha-nosein al gaban חייב. chayav. You're חייב chayav even
though it is obviously somewhere it went higher than עשרה טפחים asara
tefachim to get on top of the rock which is עשרה טפחים.
asara tefachim. So אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said, אימא דמתניתין במחט.
Eima de-matnisin be-machat. Maybe when our משנה Mishna is talking about a
needle. So it's not really higher than עשרה טפחים. asara tefachim. Of
course, even a needle has some height. So they said, so במחט.
be-machat. מחט נמי, Machat nami, a needle also אי אפשר דלא מדלייא
פורתא, ee efshar de-lo midalya purta, so it's not possible that it
doesn't rise up a little bit. It has some height to it.
So דאית ליה מורשא de-is lei mursha אי נמי דרמיא בחריצא. ee
nami de-ramya be-charitza. Basically, maybe though it's a needle and it's going
into a crevice.
So here is your rock, which is, you
know, עשרה טפחים asara tefachim in the רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabim, okay?
And imagine, I guess, that you've got like a crack in the
rock, okay, like this. Okay. So what you did is, here you're
standing, okay, I don't know, here you are, okay, on the rock.
You're standing here and you are putting your needle into this crack
in the rock. So the needle never gets, you see, you see
what I'm drawing? The needle never gets higher than עשרה טפחים. asara
tefachim. Now, you would say, okay, but then why are you חייב?
chayav? Because it's not on the base, it's not on the top
of רשות היחיד. Reshus HaYachid. Only if it's here it's רשות היחיד?
Reshus HaYachid? No, because this is a רשות היחיד, Reshus HaYachid, even
little cracks on the floor of a רשות היחיד Reshus HaYachid are
called the holes of רשות היחיד Reshus HaYachid and count as well.
So you got it from underneath into a hole in the base
of the floor of רשות היחיד Reshus HaYachid without ever getting it
higher than עשרה טפחים. asara tefachim. Now, that sounds like a pretty
crazy scenario and you understand why they were all telling him it's
a משנה. Mishna. I mean, you're going to say the whole משנה
Mishna is talking about this case? Now the other question to ask
is, and maybe this is more significant, is, what kind of a
question is that? All along we've been dealing with cases, you take
it from a רשות הרבים, Reshus HaRabim, you walk through a כרמלית,
karmelis, you put it down in a רשות היחיד. Reshus HaYachid. Who
ever thought that it couldn't, like, go through momentarily? Or we said
if you carried it higher than עשרה טפחים asara tefachim in a
רשות הרבים Reshus HaRabim and then you stopped, right, even though the
whole four אמות amos were higher than עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, it's
okay. Why should any of this matter? So תוספות Tosafos says he's
really asking a much more specific special case question. His question is
only about throwing. All those cases were carrying and here's his question.
His question is you threw it up and then it came to
its apex and then it fell down. So because it came to
its height at מקום פטור makom patur and then it changed directions
and fell down by gravity and not by your energy, maybe that's
seen as a separate type of an act. And since it occurred,
normally of course if I use gravity it's fine. I mean, it's
obviously still my action. But because the gravity took over and my
energy stopped and that switch happened in the מקום פטור makom patur
higher than עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, maybe that breaks it up into
two acts and therefore the second part of the act was from
a מקום פטור makom patur into a רשות היחיד. Reshus HaYachid. So
it's not just that it happened to go through. We've talked about
that before and you're חייב. chayav. It's that it switched directions and
switched the energy, as it were, in the מקום פטור makom patur
and that maybe makes it a separate act that makes me exempt.
Now if that's the whole case, then okay, that's a very interesting
question. But you then you didn't need the crazy scenario of the
needle. You would just say our משנה Mishna is talking about that
you directly put it down. Your question is a very interesting question
of if you threw it and then it fell down. Okay, so
תוספות Tosafos says yeah, but we wanted to somehow, you know, make
the משנה Mishna work under even, you know, in all cases. But
anyway, I just want to put that out there because even before
you got to the משנה, Mishna, it seems like a bizarre question
about why should it be exempt just because it flew momentarily, you
know, higher than עשרה טפחים? asara tefachim? And תוספות Tosafos specifically describes
this case where
the
act switches direction.
Yeah, or if you just threw it directly horizontally. It didn't hit
an apex and come down. You threw it like this and then
it just sort of landed there. It was never sort of that
type of a change. So right, those were the so anyway it's
a very interesting question if that's the question, but then you know
you don't exactly understand why the גמרא Gemara focused on the משנה.
Mishna. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
אמר רב מישא. Amar Rav Mesha. So רב מישא Rav Mesha said,
בעי רבי יוחנן. Ba'ei Rebbe Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan asked, we
didn't get an answer. רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan asked, כל דברשות הרבים
גבוה עשרה ואינו רחב ארבע. Kol div'reshus harabbim gavoha asara ve'eino rachav
arba. You have a wall in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, it's ten
high, it's not four wide, it should be ארבע arba with a
ה, hei, it's not four wide, the wall itself is not a
רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
ומוקף לכרמלית Umukaf lecarmelis and you use this wall to go around
some type of an open space, some type of a park, some
yard, a
כרמלית. carmelis. ועשאו רשות היחיד, Ve'asao reshus hayachid, and now the space
inside the wall is רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. You've got a wall
around your backyard. Let's just say that the wall itself is not
four wide, is not a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, but it turned
your backyard into a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. וזרק ונח על גביו.
Vezarak venach al gabav. Now you threw something not and it didn't
land in your backyard. Your backyard now is רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
It landed on top of the wall. What is the status of
the top of the wall? The wall taken by itself is not
רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, it's not four wide. Okay, but it makes
the backyard רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So does the width of the
wall itself become now a part of that רשות היחיד reshus hayachid
as well? That's the question.
According to תוספות Tosfos as opposed to the משנה Mishna was that's
right...
according to תוספות, Tosfos, no, because תוספות Tosfos was that the actual
width of the wall was conceived of as being four טפחים. tefachim.
Since you included the gap in between, the hole, it was seen
as one unit with a width of four טפחים. tefachim.
But that implies that the width of the wall is part of
the...
Oh, you would want to say according to תוספות Tosfos if you
had a wall going around a huge area, right, that you would
actually sort of imaginarily put a board here and do the same
thing? I don't think so. I think this is very specific because
it's all part of the apparatus of the board. Okay, so that's
the question.
So it says,
where was it?
מהו? Mahu?
Do we say, מהו? Mahu? כיון דאינו רחב ארבע מקום פטור הוא?
Keivan de'eino rachav arba makom patur hu? Since it's not four, it's
a מקום פטור, makom patur, right? A כרמלית carmelis is four but
it's not it doesn't have other parameters, it doesn't have ten high,
but not even being four wide makes it a מקום פטור. makom
patur. So the top of the wall is totally okay. או דילמא,
O dilma, or do we say, כיון דעשאו רשות היחיד, Keivan de'asao
reshus hayachid, since it turned your backyard into a רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid, כמאן דמלי דמיא? Keman demali damya? It's like your backyard is
all one unit, filled, and this is part of your backyard, part
of that רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Again, this like we had this
idea before like a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid is like it's filled,
but basically it's all part of the רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and
in itself is a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Okay. אמר עולא, Amar
Ulla, and by the way, I thought what Michael was going to
ask was because the other point about the hole in the rock
was like the idea that a hole like in the floors of
a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid are considered part of the רשות היחיד.
reshus hayachid. So isn't it obvious if holes are part of the
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid shouldn't the thickness of the wall be as
well? So there תוספות Tosfos says, yeah, but a hole is like
an easy thing to use. You like store your objects in the
holes in the floor. The top of the wall presumably is not
so usable, so it wasn't so obvious what we would consider to
be the thickness of the wall. I know, I understand. Well, that's
if it's lower than nine. This is higher than ten. אמר עולא,
Amar Ulla, אמר עולא Ulla said, קל וחומר, Kal vachomer, of course,
it's a קל וחומר kal vachomer that the thickness of the wall
is a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. ומה היא עושה מחיצה לאחרים לעצמה
לא כל שכן? Umah hi osa mechitza la'acherim le'atzma lo kol shekein?
If it's considered a wall for the backyard, you know, it makes
the backyard into a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, it should certainly make
itself into a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So whatever that קל וחומר
kal vachomer is like, what is it? Like the... what is it,
the shoemaker's children are always the last to have shoes, right? So
it's making the backyard רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, how about for itself?
But yeah, it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Basically, it becomes part
of the רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, it creates the רשות היחיד, reshus
hayachid, so certainly its thickness is also considered רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid.
איתמר נמי, Itmar nami, it was also said, אמר רב חסדא אמר
רב, Amar Rav Chisda Amar Rav, הכי נמי אמר רבי יצחק אמר
רבי יוחנן. Hachi nami amar Rebbe Yitzchak amar Rebbe Yochanan. So it
said in the name of רב Rav or name of רבי יוחנן,
Rebbe Yochanan, כל דברשות הרבים גבוה עשרה ואינו רחב ארבע. Kol div'reshus
harabbim gavoha asara ve'eino rachav arba. You have this wall that's ten
high, but it's not four wide. ומוקף לכרמלית, Umukaf lecarmelis, but it's
surrounding a כרמלית. carmelis. ועשאו רשות היחיד, Ve'asao reshus hayachid, it makes
the כרמלית carmelis into a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. הזורק ונח על
גביו חייב. Hazarak venach al gabav chayav. If it lands on the
width of the wall, the height... you know, not in the backyard
but on the top of the wall, on its width, you're חייב.
chayav. ומה היא עושה מחיצה. Umah hi osa mechitza. If it makes
a wall for the actual כרמלית, carmelis, it turns your backyard into
a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, לעצמה לא כל שכן? Le'atzma lo kol
shekein? Certainly it will make itself a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. It's
all part of the רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Okay.
But if it is actually wide four? Then then it's its own
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and then it's making it's like two רשות
היחיד? reshus hayachid?
Yeah.
So okay, what's the deal? בעי רבי יוחנן, Ba'ei Rebbe Yochanan, now
רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan asked, בור תשעה ועקר ממנו חוליה והשלימה לעשרה.
Bor tisha ve'akar mimeno chulya vehishlima la'asara. You have a well that's
only nine deep. You went and on שבת Shabbos you pulled up
a mound of earth, like you shoveled out a mound of earth.
from that well and you made it into, now it's ten deep.
Now you might be חייב chayav for בונה boneh or חורש, choreish,
but fine, besides that, you dug the extra extra טפח, tefach, you
threw it over your back, the dirt flew out and went into
the רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. Have you also carried from רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid to רשות הרבים? reshut harabim? Because it only became רשות
היחיד reshut hayachid as you were removing the dirt and the dirt
is the object that you're carrying. So what do we say? All
right.
So where were we? So מאי? mai? What do we say? עקירת
חפץ ועשיית מחיצה בהדי הדדי קאתו ומחייב? akirat chefetz v'asiyat mechitza bahadi
hadadi ka'atu umichayev? The uprooting of the object and the making of
the מחיצה mechitza of עשרה טפחים asara tefachim came at the same
time and therefore we'll consider it as though it was all there
already and therefore you're חייב. chayav. You took an object from a
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid because in the act of taking it became
רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. או לא חייב? o lo chayav? Or we
would say
no because it didn't start as רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, it was
only after I took. ואם תמצי לומר, v'im timtzi lomar, and if
you want to say כיון דלא הוי מחיצה עשרה מעיקרא, keivan d'lo
havei mechitza asara me'ikara, since it didn't start by having the wall,
it didn't start as רשות היחיד reshut hayachid when I started to
remove the dirt, לא חייב, lo chayav, I'm not חייב. chayav. It
only became רשות היחיד reshut hayachid after I moved the dirt or
during. That's not enough to make it an act of taking from
רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Here's a different question I have, similar but
from the flip side. בור עשרה ונתן לתוכו חוליה ומיעטו. bor asara
v'natan l'tocho chulya u'mi'ato. I took a mound of dirt from outside
of the well from רשות הרבים reshut harabim and I threw it
into the well. It went into the well and now it made
it from עשרה טפחים asara tefachim deep to תשעה טפחים tisha tefachim
deep. Am I חייב? chayav? Did I go from רשות הרבים reshut
harabim into רשות היחיד reshut hayachid because by the time the action
started that was a real רשות הרבים reshut harabim and a real
רשות היחיד? reshut hayachid? Or do we say by the time the
action ended and the dirt fell onto the base, it stopped being
רשות היחיד reshut hayachid and I'm exempt?
You could say קלוטה כמי שהונחה דמיא. kluta k'mi shehuncha damya.
Okay, that might be true if you got to say קלוטה כמי
שהונחה דמיא kluta k'mi shehuncha damya or כמאן דמליא דמי, k'man d'malya
dami, but if we're not saying that, that's a very good point.
So what do you say? או לא חייב. o lo chayav. So
it says
מאי? mai? What do we say? הנחת חפץ וסילוק מחיצה בהדי הדדי
קאתו ומחייב? hanachat chefetz v'siluk mechitza bahadi hadadi ka'atu umichayev? Do we
say putting the object down and removing the מחיצה mechitza came at
the same time and therefore you're חייב? chayav? It's funny, you're חייב
chayav meaning because because it came at the same time and therefore
we say that
we don't have to yet pay attention to the going away of
the wall. We could say that since it came at the same
time it's not as if it was still there when it was
being put down. או לא חייב. o lo chayav. Or would we
say not, that since by the end of the action the wall
no longer existed you'd be exempt. So the גמרא Gemara says תיפשוט
ליה מדידיה. tipshot lei mididei.
Why don't you prove this from a statement he himself makes? דתנן,
detnan, because we taught a משנה: Mishnah: הזורק
ארבע אמות בכותל למעלה מעשרה טפחים. hazorek arba amot bekotel l'ma'ala me'asara
tefachim. If you threw ארבע אמות arba amot and threw something that
hit a wall, like the גמרא Gemara says it's like a sticky
thing of like dates or whatever so it hits the wall and
sticks there. You threw something against a wall and it first traveled
ארבע אמות arba amot from רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. So
למעלה מעשרה טפחים, l'ma'ala me'asara tefachim, if it flies, if it's going
higher than עשרה טפחים asara tefachim and hits the wall higher than
עשרה, asara, כזורק באויר, k'zorek ba'avir, it's like you threw it in
the air, you didn't do anything, it was higher than the airspace.
למטה מעשרה, l'mata me'asara, if it's under עשרה, asara, within עשרה טפחים,
asara tefachim, כזורק בארץ, k'zorek ba'aretz, it's like you threw it on
the ground. והזורק בארבע אמות חייב v'hazorek b'arba amot chayav and if
you threw ארבע אמות arba amot you're חייב. chayav. Okay, all that's
interesting. How's this relevant? So ואבינא בה v'avina bah and we said
והלא נח, v'halo nach, I don't get it, even if it went
ארבע אמות arba amot and was under עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, it
hit the wall and then it bounced off. It didn't come to
a rest. A normal object would bounce off the wall. ואמר רבי
יוחנן v'amar Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said בדבילה שמנה
שנו. bidveila shemena shanu. No,
we're talking about like a
sticky clump of dates and therefore it hits the wall and it
sticks on the wall and therefore it doesn't and therefore it comes
to a rest. Okay, now how's this relevant to our question? Because
here's the גמרא's Gemara point. That was רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and
before the other statement was a question of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
And here's why we think that we have an answer. ואמאי? v'amai?
Why are you חייב chayav in this case? הא קמבצר מארבע אמות.
ha kamivtzar me'arba amot.
It's not really a full ארבע אמות
arba amot because if you throw exactly ארבע אמות arba amot and
then it hits. Right, right. Now why
is it not a full ארבע אמות? arba amot?
So רש"י Rashi says,
like Michael had said, that here
you are, you're in the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, okay, here's your
wall, okay, this is ארבע אמות, arba amot, you throw the date,
the date sticks on the wall, so the back of the date
is less than ארבע אמות arba amot removed. That's the way רש"י
Rashi explains the question. The גמרא's Gemara answer is, so now, so
fine. So תוספות Tosafot says that cannot be because if that were
true you really would be exempt. It's like the case of the
basket. Remember the basket that a little part of the basket remained
inside? So who cares about סילוק מחיצות siluk mechitzot or anything, the
architecture, the reality is part of the object remains less than ארבע
אמות. arba amot. תוספות Tosafot says that cannot be the issue. So
that's not the case. תוספות Tosafot says I don't get it, you
threw the whole thing שש אמות, shesh amot, the edge of it
went ארבע אמות. arba amot. That's not my issue. What's my issue?
My issue is if you now have this big clump of dates
stuck to a wall and it's under ten טפחים, tefachim, okay, he
says, this area now,
this down here is no longer if we said this between two
structures of רשות הרבים reshus harabim then this area is directly underneath
it is no longer a רשות הרבים reshus harabim because you've got
a thing coming out of a wall, you can't travel underneath it,
you can't get underneath it, okay? So therefore if this area underneath
it isn't a רשות הרבים reshus harabim it's not coming to land
in a רשות הרבים.
reshus harabim. Okay, created its own little space that's not big of
a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, okay, and therefore why are you חייב?
chayav?
Okay, so that's, anyway, that's the way תוספות Tosafos understands the question.
Doesn't exactly fit the word נמיכי מארבע אמות, nemichai me'arba amos, but
the point is is that it's no longer in a space of
a רשות הרבים reshus harabim anymore. So what so אלא, ella, so
what do you see rather? So it says
אלא והתם, ella ve'hasam, so you see that we don't care that
it changes the architecture by the end of the act. We go
by what it looked like at the beginning of the act. So
the גמרא Gemara says no that's not comparable. התם לא מבטלי, hasam
lo mevatlei, you're not going to leave that thing of dates stuck
to the wall. You haven't really changed the architecture. Temporarily there's a
bump on the wall. Okay. But the space is still רשות הרבים.
reshus harabim. Nobody thinks the basic structure has changed. הכא מבטלי. hacha
mevatlei. Here if you throw dirt into the well you are really
changing the structure. So don't be cute there and say you now
have a bump on a wall. That's temporary. My question is when
you throw dirt in a well and you really change the structure,
do we define the act by the beginning and say you're חייב
chayav or do we say at the end it's no longer a
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and you are exempt. Okay, and the גמרא
Gemara does not have an answer. Let's do one more question. בעי
רבא, ba'ei Rava, רבא Rava asked. זרק
דף ונח על גבי יתידות מהו? zarak daf venach al gabei yesedos
mahu? You went ahead and here you had you had two like
pegs here, at least ten טפחים tefachim high, okay, but again it
was not like four טפחים tefachim wide, it was not, you know,
they were separate pegs, okay? And you went ahead and it wasn't
like the it wasn't like the walls of a well where we
say it's because you can combine them they're already combined. These are
just סתם stam two separate posts out there in the middle of
somewhere. You throw a a a plank and it lands on top
and now it turned it into a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So
same type of a thing. The plank is the object. The object
that you're throwing is also making it into a רשות היחיד. reshus
hayachid. So we've already seemingly answered that question. We said since it
didn't start as רשות היחיד reshus hayachid at the beginning you're not
going to be חייב chayav if it even if at the end
it now is a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. זרק דף zarak daf one minute ונח על
גבי יתידות venach al gabei yesedos you threw this plank and it
landed on these pegs מהו mahu what do we say? גמרא Gemara
says מאי קמיבעיא ליה mai kamibaya lei what's the question? הנחת חפץ
ועשיית מחיצה בהדדי קאתו? hanachas chefetz ve'asiyas mechitza behadadi ka'atu?
If you're asking what we looked at before, the same thing we
asked before, the putting down of the object, in that act of
putting down, made it into a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So that's
true, היינו דרבי יוחנן. hainu de'Rabbi Yochanan.
That's what that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said earlier, right? If
in the act of like removing the object, digging out the well,
you turned it into רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. Same point here. When
you started you didn't have רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and we were
inclined to say that therefore you'd be exempt if you didn't start
with רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So the same should be true here.
What makes this case different? So the גמרא Gemara says no. כי
קמיבעיא ליה לרבא ki kamibaya lei le'Rava here's what רבא's Rava question
was.
כגון דזרק דף וחפץ על גביו. kegon dezarak daf vecheifetz al gabav.
You didn't just throw a plank. You threw a plank that had
some some something on it. So you threw the plank, it lands,
and it lands with the object. So I know you're not חייב
chayav on the plank, okay, because the plank turned it into a
רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and the thing that turns it in can't
also be the object that you've carried and so on. What I
want to know is do we say well now it became רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid and then the object on top of this came
to land so you're חייב chayav for the object or
not.
All at the same time?
It's okay, let's take a look. So what do we say?
מהו? mahu? So the גמרא Gemara says מהו? mahu? כיון דבהדי הדדי
קאתו? keivan debehadi hadadi ka'atu? כהנחת חפץ ועשיית מחיצה דמי? kehanachas chefetz
ve'asiyas mechitza dami? Like Michael just said, since it's all one big
thing and one, you know, it's all sort of happening at the
same time, so it's the same point. It was not a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid before the object landed, only after the object landed.
או דלמא o dilma or do we say כיון דלא אפשר דלא
מדליא פורתא? keivan delo efshar delo midalya porta? If you're throwing a
plank with something on it, that thing is going to move a
little bit, it's going to, you know, in the middle air, it's
going to, you know, rise up and fall back down. It's not
going to be glued onto the object. Since it's impossible that it's
not removed a little bit
והדר נייח ve'hadar nayach and then it sort of they both plonk
down at plonk down, but that it then there is like a
momentary second where they're
recombining so כעשיית מחיצה והנחת חפץ דמי. ke'asiyas mechitza vehanachas chefetz dami.
That's like first you made it into רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and
then you put it down. And therefore you actually would be חייב
chayav because it actually did happen in two cases, in two steps.
So the גמרא Gemara says תיקו. teiku. We don't know the answer.
Although with that I should say that the גמרא Gemara it seems
from that it would be obvious that if you did actually, you
know, you did actually,
if they were really separated you First this fell and then that
fell, you'd be חייב, chayav, even though when you threw it there
didn't yet exist a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, right? As long as
that when it landed, the object landed, first there was a רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid and then it landed, then you would be חייב,
chayav, even though when you began the process it didn't yet exist,
but you were controlling the process and you made it exist along
the way, that would be enough. So we will continue with these
types of discussions of carrying tomorrow. Alright.